<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Royall and gracious priviledges, granted by the high and mighty Philip the fourth King of Spaine, &amp;c. March 19. 1645. Vnto the English merchants trading within his dominions. / Translated out of Spanish, and published for the benefit of such, who desire commerce in those parts.</title>
            <author>Spain. Sovereign (1621-1665 : Philip IV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E292_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200157</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860962</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860962</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113089</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113089)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 48:E292[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Royall and gracious priviledges, granted by the high and mighty Philip the fourth King of Spaine, &amp;c. March 19. 1645. Vnto the English merchants trading within his dominions. / Translated out of Spanish, and published for the benefit of such, who desire commerce in those parts.</title>
                  <author>Spain. Sovereign (1621-1665 : Philip IV)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, at the Princes Armes in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>British --  Spain --  Government policy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Commercial policy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113089:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ROYALL AND GRACIOVS PRIVILEDGES, GRANTED By the High and Mighty <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>March</hi> 19. 1645. Vnto the Engliſh Merchants Trading within His Dominions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Spaniſh, and Publiſhed for the Benefit of ſuch,</hi> who deſire Commerce in thoſe parts.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> at the Princes Armes in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113089:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113089:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoever is vers'd in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Merchandizing, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the myſtery of Forraign Trade, muſt confeſſe what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary advantages accrue to this Kingdome by Commerce with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions annexed to that Crowne, as well for the Exportation of our owne Manufactures and Commodities, as for the importation of theirs, eſpecially that of Treaſure, elſe how could our Mint find matter enough to worke upon? Nor is ours alone, but moſt of the Mints of <hi>Europ</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to the Mines of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru;</hi> Nor Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Mints onely, but the <hi>Turk</hi> makes his aſpers, the <hi>Ruſſe</hi> makes his Rubbles of Spaniſh Rialls, Inſomuch that one may ſay, the Coyne of <hi>Spaine</hi> is more Catholique then her King. And as our trade and amitie with <hi>Spain</hi> is gainfull, ſo is it very ancient; For the Spaniards to this day reſpect the Engliſh, as much as any other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb facs="tcp:113089:3"/>Nation, and there are many inducements ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. The Chronicle tell us how our Black Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd one of their Kings to his Crown; the Alliance 'twixt the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Portugall,</hi> is yet freſh amongſt them; Some of our Kings ſent them Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries againſt the <hi>Moores,</hi> beſides divers other Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; And the ſtory tells us what excellent Queenes the <hi>Infanta's</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> have prov'd with us. Adde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto our ancient and famous League with the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> wherof this King is the chiefeſt branch; All theſe are obligations for <hi>Spaine</hi> to eſteem us, and us them interchangeably, which we did, till the difference of Religion happen'd, and our aſſiſting the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> with the Invaſion intended in the yeare <hi>1588.</hi> And though we have been at diſtance with the <hi>Spaniard</hi> ever ſince, yet he ſeemes to retaine ſtill the Nationall eſteem he had alwayes of us; It being one of his maine maximes of policy; <hi>Con todo el mundo guerra, y paz con In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galatierra;</hi> Warre with all the world, and peace with <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Engliſh Merchants have obtain'd from time to time divers priviledges in the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which have been but looſely obſerv'd; This follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Declaration or Royall grant, is not onely a confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but an enlargement of thoſe Priviledges, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are exempted from all oaths and queſtions touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Religion, which before they were ſubject unto in ſome caſes. Their Corne is not to be anticipated or taken away from them by any Officer for ſupply of the Kings Armies or Magazins, till they have made their market; They ſhall not bee moleſted, much leſſe impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:113089:3"/>for any putrified or ill conditioned fiſh, but it muſt be onely throwne oreboard. Their bookes of Accompts are not to be ſeiz'd upon, or medled with by any Officer; There ſhall be no rate as heretofore impos'd upon their fiſh, or any preemption forced upon them, but they ſhall bee left free to ſet their owne prices. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are permitted to chooſe and nominate a Iudge to be their <hi>Conſervator,</hi> who ſhall have power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all ſuites and differences 'twixt them and any other, ſo that they ſhall not need hereafter to be toſſed from one Court to another, but make their addreſſe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their owne Iudge, whom they may change when they pleaſe, and ther's no appeale from him to any other Court, unleſſe it bee to the High Counſell of State. Beſides, they have priviledge now to ſearch for any old Record that may concerne their immunities, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could not.</p>
            <p>And if our Merchants trading into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and there reſident, were ſo carefull as they ought to bee, they would make better uſe of that Kings indulgence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; for thoſe of <hi>Sivill,</hi> had of late a Royall grant to purchaſe and incloſe a piece of ground, for a Cymitrey or buriall place, but they ſlighting this favour of grace, immodeſtly expoſe their dead bodyes unto the ſcorne and outrage of the rude multitude, but I hope, and heartily wiſh, That the propenſitie of that King to doe our Nation good, may incourage thoſe whom it may concerne to be as provident to obtaine ſome immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities for the good of their ſoules and bodies, as for their eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:113089:4"/>Theſe Compliances of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, I thought expedient to publiſh unto the world, that wee by way of civill correſpondence ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Merchants and Subjects of that Crowne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Friend, <hi>I. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113089:4"/>
            <head>The Copie of a Patent, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeverall gracious Priviledges lately granted by the High and Mighty <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>On Philip</hi> by the grace of God, King of <hi>Caſtile, Leon, Aragon,</hi> the two <hi>Sicilies, Ieruſalem, Portugal, Navarre, Granado, Toledo, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencia, Galiſia, Maliorca, Sivill, Sardonia, Cordova, Corſega, Murica, Iaen,</hi> the <hi>Algarues, Algeſira Gibraltar,</hi> the Iſlands of the <hi>Canaries,</hi> the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, Iſlands and firme Land of the Ocean Sea, Arch-Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy, Brabant</hi> and <hi>Milan,</hi> Earle of <hi>Haſpurg, Handers, Tiroll</hi> and <hi>Barſelona,</hi> Lord of <hi>Biſcay</hi> and <hi>Molina,</hi> &amp;c,</p>
            <p>Whereas on the behalfe of you <hi>Richard An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> Conſul of the Engliſh Nation, for your ſelfe, and in the name of the Subjects of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113089:5"/>King of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> it hath been ſhewed unto me, that by vertue of the peace, which is concluded in this and that Realme, you doe reſide and trade in <hi>Andaluſia,</hi> and ſpecially in the Cities of <hi>Sivill,</hi> St. <hi>Lucar. Cadiz,</hi> and <hi>Malaga,</hi> Deſiring me to be pleaſed to confirme unto you the Priviledges, exemptions and faculties, which do belong unto you, as well by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the ſaid Peace, as by the confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof, and other favours and graces, which my Lord and Father of Glorious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, did grant unto you, and all ſuch others, which have been given you by the Crownes of my Realmes of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> and to command, that they may be in, and for all things obſerved and accompliſhed unto you, without any limitation; And for fuller aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to grant them anew unto you, with the qualities, amplitudes, conditions, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which ſhall be moſt convenient for you, and to ſet penalties upon ſuch as ſhall contradict, and not obſerve them unto you. And to the end it may be known, what they are, to grant them Copies thereof, or of that which my favour ſhall be; And I taking the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113089:5"/>premiſes into conſideration, and becauſe for the occaſions which I have for my warres, you have offered to ſerve me, with two thouſand and five hundred Duccats of ſilver, to be paid one thouſand ready money, and the remaining one thouſand and five hundred in the month of <hi>April,</hi> of this yeare (whereof the Licenciate <hi>Francis Moreno,</hi> with in reverſion of <hi>Don An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony de Campo Redondo y Rio,</hi> Knight of the order of <hi>Santiago,</hi> one of my Councell and Chamber, and of the Treaſury, in your name, and by vertue of your power did acknowledge a writing of obligation in forme before <hi>Iohn Cortez de la Cruz,</hi> my Notary) I do hold it for good; And by theſe preſents of my own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and certain knowledge, and Royall and abſolute power, which I in this behalfe will make uſe of, and do uſe as an abſolute King and Lord, not acknowledging any ſuperiour in matters Temporall, doe confirme and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Priviledges, exemptions and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which do belong unto you, as well by the Articles of the ſaid peace, as by the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, and alſo the other favours and graces, which my Lord and Father did grant unto you, and others whatſoever which have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113089:6"/>been given, by my Crowns of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall</hi> unto the ſaid Subjects, in and for all things, as therein, and every thing and part therof is ſpecified, contained and declared, to the end they may be firme, ſtable, and of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and be obſerved, kept, and accompliſhed unto you. For my deliberate intent and will is, that all thoſe of the ſaid Nation, ſhall enjoy thereof, without any limitation, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that, during the time the ſaid Engliſhmen ſhall reſide in <hi>Andaluſia,</hi> neither you, nor they, may be charged with any Office nor publique charge, nor Counſell, Tutorſhip, Curatorſhip, Receivers, or Treaſurers, although they be of Cuſtomes and Millions, or other Services which concerne my Royall Treaſury; And much leſſe they may demand of you any Loans or Donations, or take from you any rights, or your rents, horſes, or ſlaves. And to doe you the more favour or grace, according to that which is agreed by the ſaid Peace, I do will and promiſe, that you ſhall and may deal and trade freely, and ſell your Merchandizes and Fruites, and buy thoſe of my Realms, and carry them forth, obſerving that which is ordained and commanded by the Lawes &amp; Statutes, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113089:6"/>make mention thereof; and paying to my Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Treaſurie the Duties or Cuſtomes which ought to be paid; Prohibiting, as I doe prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and command, not to take from you by force, any Merchandiſes, Wheat nor Barley, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be for the making ready, or furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Armies, Fleets, or Gallions, nor for purveyors or Stewards, and the priviledges are to be concerning the Wheat and Barly, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Tax, and concerning the other things and Merchandiſes, as you ſhall conclude and agree, but they may not take them out of your poſſeſſion, untill they ſhall have paid for them, unleſſe for the ſame there be leave given, that they doe not moleſt or trouble you. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as many of you doe treat to bring into the Ports of <hi>Andaluſia,</hi> the City of <hi>Sivill,</hi> and other places, great quantity of <hi>Newfoundland</hi> fiſh, and other ſorts of dry and ſalted fiſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are victuals which are very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that you have been, and are put to great charges, and are much troubled; I doe will and command, to be kept, the Ordinance of the City of <hi>Sivill,</hi> whereby it is ordained, that thoſe which come in with dry or ſalted Fiſh, there ſhall not be any price or rate ſet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113089:7"/>upon them, but they ſhall be permitted to ſell at ſuch a price as they ſhall thinke good, and it ſhall not be neceſſary to manifeſt them any more, then unto my Officers which receive my Royall rents, and if the ſhips wherein the ſaid Fiſh is brought be great ſhips, that they cannot goe up the River, and that the ſame be put into Barks or Lighters, the ludge of the Admiralty, nor any other perſon, may not put any Weighters or keepers into the Barkes or Lighters, at the charge of the owners of them.</p>
            <p>And I doe alſo command, that if the ſaid Fiſh ſhall appeare to be rotten, and that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſpent, that it be burnt, or thrown into the Sea, and that for this cauſe, there ſhall not be any cauſe or action commenced againſt the owners thereof, or perſons which ſhall ſell it, nor they ſhall not be impriſoned nor informed againſt. And foraſmuch as the Adminiſtrator of the Cuſtomes and others, of divers duties which are received for the Fruits and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes, do uſe when any body doth inform, to have the perſon impriſoned, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe to be party, whereby happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the men of Trade, great diſcredit, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and vexations. My will is, and I doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113089:7"/>that in the ſaid Informations there ſhall be only proceeded againſt the Merchandiſes, and not againſt the perſons, but they ſhall be permitted (as I doe permit them) to make, and they ſhall make their defences in the ſaid vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And foraſmuch alſo as according to an Article of the ſaid Peace, which maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of matter in Religion, notwithſtanding that in ſome ſuites, they ſhould declare whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Roman Catholiques or not, excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves to give faith to the oathes which they take, as parties or as witneſſes.</p>
            <p>I doe alſo command, that concerning this matter, there be not done, nor there ſhall not be done any thing with thoſe which are borne in the ſaid Realme, but only, that the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be kept, and accompliſhed, and that no ſuch queſtions be put unto them, giving, unto the Oathes which they ſhal take in Iudgement Court, and without, the ſame faith and credit, which ſhould be given in caſe they were Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, and herein you ſhall not receive any trouble or moleſtation, nor there ſhall not be any grievance done unto you; And whereas for the Iuſtification of ſome Cauſes, the Iudges and Iuſtices doe pretend, that the Merchants of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113089:8"/>the ſaid Nation, ſhould exhibit the Bookes of their Contractations or dealings, and are for this matter troubled and moleſted, I doe will and Command, that the Bookes of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the ſaid Nation, ſhall not be taken out of their hands for any cauſe whatſoever, but they ſhall keep and ſhew them in their houſes, to take out the parcell which ſhall bee appointed, and others ſhall not be demanded of them, nor there ſhall not be any other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers taken from them, upon penalty, that hee which ſhall doe here-againſt, ſhall be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to law.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as the Merchants do diſpatch the Merchandiſe from the Cuſtome-houſe of the ſaid City of <hi>Sivill</hi> of all duties; and becauſe they are many, do make up a ſheet, which is ſubſcribed and ſigned by all the officers, and remaineth in the hand of the <hi>Alcayde</hi> of the Cuſtome-houſe, for that by vertue thereof, the Merchandiſes are permitted to go forth, which are in Fardells, Packs, Trunks, and Caſes, and afterwards when they have taken them forth, and put them into their Houſes, and Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, the chiefe keeper of the Cuſtomhouſe, and the Officers of the halfe <hi>per cent,</hi> doe viſit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113089:8"/>the houſes and the goods, troubling and mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting them, demanding of them the diſparches, it ſeeming unto them, that they may detaine them, becauſe they left the diſpatches in the hands of the ſaid <hi>Alcayde</hi> of the Cuſtome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, I doe prohibit and command, that the houſes of the ſaid Merchants, ſhall not be viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor the diſpatches ſhall not, nor may not be demanded of them, in regard they have them not in their hands, and this is to be underſtood, and is underſtood, of houſes which are within the walls of the ſaid City, And to the end it may be known to you, which are of the ſaid Engliſh Nation, there is to be delivered unto you Copies of the ſaid Priviledges and exemptions, which doe concerne you, and which were granted unto you, aſwell by the Articles of the peace, as in any other manner, And for execution and accompliſhment of all the Premiſes, I doe command thoſe of my Counſell, and thoſe of my Councells, Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and Tribunalls of my Court, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents and Iudges of my Audiences, Alcaldes, and Officers of my Houſe, and Court, and Chanceries, and the Regent and ludge of the Court of Degrees of the City of <hi>Sivill,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113089:9"/>chiefe Alcaldes of the Precincts thereof, and all the Corrigedors, Aſſiſtants, and Governours, chiefe Iuſtices, and Ordinaries, aſwell in the ſaid Cities of <hi>Sivil, Cadiz, Malaga,</hi> and St. <hi>Lucar de Barameda,</hi> as of all other Cities, Townes, and places of theſe my Realmes and Dominions, and all other Iudges and Iuſtices whatſoever, of what quality or condition ſoever they may be, whom principally or incedentally may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne in any manner the accompliſhment or performance of that which is contained in this Patent, that preſently ſo ſoone as they ſhall be, by vertue thereof, required, or the Copie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſigned by a Notary publique, that there be thereunto given, as much faith as unto the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, and that every one in the place, where it ſhall concerne him, doe obſerve and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh; and cauſe the ſame to be obſerved, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed and executed, in and for all things as therein is contained, and they ſhall not in all, or in part, put upon you any impediments, nor any other difficulties or doubt, nor doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing againſt the tenor and forme thereof, nor conſent or give way, that it be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, limited or ſuſpended in all, or in part, or that to the contrary be given any <hi>Sedulas</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113089:9"/>or other diſpatches, but for obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, in the place which ſhall concerne every one, they ſhall give order and ordaine, to deliver unto you thoſe which ſhall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; And for more firmneſſe or validity of the favour or grace, which by this my Patent I doe grant you, and that at all times this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour may be certaine and ſure unto you, you are to keep or have a Iudge <hi>Conſervator</hi> in <hi>Anda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſia,</hi> eſpecially in the ſaid Cities of <hi>Sivill, Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga, Cadiz,</hi> and St. <hi>Lucar de Barameda,</hi> unto whom I am to give ſufficient Commiſſion, for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and accompliſhing of the ſaid Priviledges, Liberties, and exemptions, who ſhall conſtrain and compel all &amp; whatſoever, perſons, of what ſort or quality they may be, that ſhall concerne the ſaid Nation, aſwel thoſe which ſhal be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants, accuſed, as thoſe which ſhal be Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs, although the perſons which ſhall accuſe them, and which ſhall be accuſed by them, have private Iudges, aſwell by conſent as agreement, which they may have made by preheminence or priviledge, which they hold, to the end the ſaid Iudge Conſervator, may onely take knowledge privately of the ſaid Cauſes, and not any other Iudge or tribunall, although it be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113089:10"/>by way of Exceſs, or notorious Iuſtice, or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other manner or forme. Which Iudge Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator is now Doctor <hi>Don Franciſco de Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gara,</hi> Iudge of my Court <hi>de los Grados</hi> of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Sivill,</hi> the time that he ſhall aſſiſt therein, and in his abſence the Licenciate <hi>Don Franciſco de Medrano,</hi> Iudge of the ſame Court, who for the ſuites which ſhall bee commenced in the ſaid Cities of <hi>Cadiz, Malaga,</hi> and St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> is to Subdelegate his Conſervatorſhip, in the perſon which by the ſaid Nation ſhall bee propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or named, that he may affect the ſame, to the concluſion, and they ſhall be referred unto him, to be determined, and of that which he ſhall determine; the appeale is to be made to my Councell, and not to any other Court.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as my will is, that every one in his time, ſhall have primative Commiſſion and Iuriſdiction, to protect and defend you, concerning all the contents of this my Patent, that all the ſame may be kept and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the forme which I doe offer the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I have found good to charge, as by theſe preſents I doe charge them, with the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and defence hereof, and I doe command them, to ſee or peruſe this my Patent, and the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113089:10"/>qualities, conditions, preheminences, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifications therein contained, and to cauſe all the ſame to be kept, accompliſhed and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in ſuch forme and manner, and according as therein is contained and declared, without conſenting, or giving way, that in all or in part, there be made unto you any doubt or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and before the ſaid <hi>Don Franciſcode Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gara,</hi> or in his abſence before the ſaid <hi>Don Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis de Medrano</hi> (and not before any other Iudge) privatly in the Firſt inſtance, are to paſſe, and be followed all the cauſes and ſuites, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Premiſes, or any thing or part thereof ſhall be moved and cauſed, and the execution and puniſhment of thoſe which ſhall not be obedient; For my will is, that the knowledge and determination of all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in this my Patent, is in all things privatly to concerne, and ſhall concerne them; proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all things againſt thoſe which ſhall be culpable, and executing for the ſame, the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are mentioned by Law, reſerving as I doe reſerve, the appellations which ſhall be put in upon their Acts and Sentences, to my Councell, and not any other Court, without that any of my other Counſells, Tribunalls,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113089:11"/>Courts, Chanceries, or any other Iudges or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of my Realmes or Dominions, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever quality they be, may meddle, or ſhall meddle therewith, or in the uſe or exerciſe of the Iuriſdiction privative in the ſaid firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which by this my Patent I doe grant unto them, by way of exceſſe appellation or any other recourſe or manner, the which and every of them, I do inhibit and hold for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the knowledge thereof and do declare them for incompetent Iudges therof, for which and every thing, &amp; part thereof, I do give them the moſt ſufficient power, and moſt ample Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which according to Law is required &amp; neceſſary, with the incidences &amp; dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies annexities, and after them the ſaid Engliſh nation of the ſaid city of <hi>Sivill,</hi> may name in the ſaid Commiſſion, one of the Iudges of the ſaid Audience, which the ſaid Nation ſhall chuſe; And I doe command the Preſident and thoſe of my Counſell of the Chamber, that preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before them their nomination (the caſe happening) to make void the ſaid Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by promotion or vacation of the ſaid <hi>Don Francis de Vergara,</hi> and <hi>Don Francis de Medrano,</hi> or to diſpatch it, in any other manner, by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113089:11"/>to him that ſhall be therein nominated, in the forme according, and as by this my Patent is declared; And that it may be the better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, I doe from this time give them power and authority, that they may ſubdeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and they ſhall ſubdeligate this Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the buſineſſe and ſuites, which ſhall be offered in the ſaid Cities of <hi>Cadiz Malaga,</hi> and St. <hi>Lucar de Barameda,</hi> in the perſon which by you ſhall be propounded unto them, that they may ſubſtantiate them for a concluſion, and remit the Suites and Cauſes, unto them to be determined, in ſuch manner, as they ſhall find good and convenient, for the ſecurity of that which is contained in this my Patent; And I doe charge the moſt Excellent Prince, <hi>Don Balthazar Charles,</hi> my moſt deare, and moſt beloved Sonne, and doe command the Infants, Prelates, Dukes, Marqueſſes, Earles, Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Commanders, and under-Commanders, Governours of Caſtles, Counſell, Preſidents Plaines, and thoſe of my Counſell, Preſidents and Iudges of my Courts, <hi>Alcaydes,</hi> and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of my Houſe, Court and Chanceries, and all the Corigidors, Aſſiſtants, Governours, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caldes, Mayors, and Ordinaries, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113089:12"/>Iudges and Iuſtices of theſe my Realmes and Dominions, to obſerve and accompliſh, and cauſe to be obſerved and accompiſhed, this my Patent, and the favour or grace which thereby I doe grant you, and againſt the tenor and forme thereof, not to doe or paſſe, now, nor at any time, in any manner perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually for ever more. Nor to conſent or give way to be limited or ſuſpended unto you, all, or part thereof, notwithſtanding whatſoever Lawes or Statutes of theſe my Realmes and Dominions, Ordinances, Stile, Vſe or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the ſaid Cities of <hi>Sivill, Cadiz, Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga,</hi> or St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> or any other thing, which is, or may be to the contrary, the which for this time (for ſo much as concerneth this matter, holding the ſame here for incerted and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated, as it were word for word written) I doe diſpence, abrogate, derogate, cancell, annihilate, and make void, and of none effect, remaining in full force and effect, for all other things hence-forward. And for this my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>Ieronimo de Canencia,</hi> Auditor of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, in my chiefe Office of Accompts, and my Secretary of the <hi>Media enate</hi> ſhall take a Copie, at whoſe charge is the accompt and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113089:12"/>reaſon of this right. And I doe declare, that for this favour you have paid the duty of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia enata,</hi> amounteth to thirty and five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand one hundred fifty and five <hi>Maravediz</hi> in ſilver, which ſum you are to pay, from fifteene to fifteen yeares perpetually, and in caſe they doe accompliſh or end, you may not make uſe of this favour untill ſuch time as it ſhall firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that you have ſatisfied this duty, and you are alſo to pay the Judge Conſervator, which ſhall be named his ſalary, or to helpe to beare his charges, which he ſhall injoy for his labour or paines in the ſaid buſineſſe, before you ſhall injoy thereof, which is to appeare by Certificate of the office of this duty. Given in <hi>Saragoſa</hi> the Nineteenth day of <hi>March, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p>I the King, I <hi>Anthony Carnero,</hi> Secretary of the King our Lord, did cauſe it to be written, by his Commandement Regiſtred. <hi>Michael de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaga,</hi> Lievtenant of the Lord High Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, <hi>Michael de Lariaga;</hi> The Copie was taken <hi>Ieronimo de Caneneia, Don Iohn Chumazero y Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillo;</hi> The Doctor <hi>Don Anthony de Campo Redon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do y Rio,</hi> the Licenciate.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:113089:13"/>
            <head>Ioſeph Gonſales.</head>
            <p>THis Copie doth agree with that out of which it was taken, which for this effect was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited unto me by <hi>William Bland,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the City of <hi>Sivill,</hi> who tooke it away againe with him the <hi>11</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> Anno <hi>1645.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ioſeph de Pineda, <hi>Notary Publick of the City of</hi> Sivil, <hi>for the King.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113089:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
